PADDY YOOSIN

Toronto, ON M5V 1A3 ● (437)994-3785 ● paddykiprop@gmail.com

Professional Summary

I am a highly motivated and skilled Senior Android Developer with extensive experience in developing and maintaining mobile applications for various industries. With a positive "I can do it" attitude and a commitment to delivering high-quality results, I approach challenges enthusiastically and believe that "everything is possible". While working with a team, I possess excellent communication and interpersonal skills, which have enabled me to perform tasks, provide feedback, and manage time effectively. With a passion for innovation and a track record of meeting deadlines, I am confident in my reliability and ability to drive success and exceed expectations.

Skills

- Native Mobile: Android development: Java programming language, Groovy, Kotlin Programming language, Android SDK, Dagger, performance, optimization and Coroutines iOS: Swift
- Cross Platform Mobile Development:
 Experience in Flutter programming language;
 Dart Platform, DevTools, Flutter widgets, State management, Stateless widgets, Stateful widgets
- API and RESTful Service Development:
 Laravel (PHP) Framework, Pure PHP, Spring
 boot, JSON, GSON, Angular Framework and
 Node Js
- Design Patterns: Solid principals, MVVM
- Cloud Services: Google cloud functions, AWS, E2C, S3, RDS
- Automation and Version Control: GitHub,
 Bitbucket, Gitlab

- IDEs, Testing and Debugging: I used tools such as ADB (Android debug bridge), Dart analyzer, JUnit and IntelliJ IDEs, Android Studio, IntelliJ idea, Visual Studio and Visual Studio code
- Front-end Development: Flutter, React.js,
 Vue.js, HTML/CSS/JS, Android XML, Material
 design patterns and Bootstrap
- Backend Development, Database & Microservices: Java, Spring Boot, Node.js, MySQL, PostgreSQL, Firebase, PHP, Laravel, EC2, Sqlite, other relational databases
- Scripting Languages: PHP, python, Groovy, Javascript, Typescript, C#
- Other: Raspberry Pi, Arduino, testing, technical documentation and technical writing, code obfuscation and other encryption techniques

Work History

Android Developer, 01/2022 to Current

Global Company for Engineering and Development (https://gecdoman.com/) – Remote, Oman

- I was responsible for maintaining and enhancing a Ghaytah **cab booking system**, which included **optimizing** the app's interaction with the Google Location APIs and Directions APIs to **lower production costs**.
- Through these efforts, I achieved an impressive 80% reduction in API monthly expenses.
- The technologies and skills utilized included: Java, Kotlin, GPS, navigation, Geolocation API, Directions API, maps, AWS, NodeJs, Play Store submission and app store submission.

Software Developer, 01/2023 to 08/2023

SmartLobby – London

Worked on two projects on contract:

Abobos Digital Signage:

- Developed **Android TV** application for **signage**, ad and display automation.
- I contributed in **improving** the **compatibility** of the application from **50% to 95%** of the devices. I upgraded the app to be compatible with android 10, 11 and 12.
- I also rewrote code to ensure **synchronization** between server ad changes and live TV streaming **without interrupting** current ad display schedule
- Technologies and skills involved include; **Java**, **Kotlin**, Spring Boot, **Flutter**, **Dart**, Bitbucket, Github, Unit Tests, SQL, MySQL, Agile development.

PlanetVCF:

- Worked on PlanetVCF application API, Contact backup management application. Improved the
 performance of the mobile application by developing a mobile version of their website and PHP
 middleware to connect with the WordPress database for the PlanetVCF application.
- The **performance enhancement** achieved a significant **20x speed improvement** on the application.
- Technologies used: **Flutter**, **Kotlin**, **PHP**, **WordPress**, **MySQL**, and **GitHub**.

Lead Mobile Developer, 07/2018 to 12/2021

Trichain Technologies (https://trichaintechnologies.com) – Murang'a, Kenya

- The tasks involved in **managing projects**, delegating duties, and overseeing project management, with a strong emphasis on mobile app development.
- Successfully delivered **over 20 projects**, comprising mobile apps for both iOS (30%) and Android (70%), highlighting a significant impact on project completion. My contribution **increased confidence rating** on Trichain by **3 points** according to the company rating standards
- Utilized a diverse range of technologies, including **Flutter**, **Java**, **Kotlin**, Spring Boot, Linux, Git, Bitbucket, PHP, Laravel, MySQL, SQL, BLE, Bluetooth Beacons and Python, showcasing a broad skill set.

- Developed in-depth knowledge of the Android SDK, performance optimization, and the
 utilization of various tools and concepts such as AsyncTasks, Adapters, Fragments, OkHttp and
 Activities. Also demonstrated proficiency in design patterns, user interface design, usability, and
 post-launch product support.
- In addition to technical skills, a strong development of management skills, including prioritization, goal orientation, **problem-solving**, **scrum**, and **collaboration**, contributing to effectiveness in project management and team coordination.

Education

Bachelor of Science: Software Engineering

Muranga University of Technology - Murang'a Kenya

Portfolio

- Abobos Digital Signage https://play.google.com/store
 /apps/details?id=com.abobos.signage.player.app
- Ghaytah Cab App. https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.fanswish
- PlanetVCF https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.planetvcf.app
- Double Dip Solutions Android https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.doubledipsolutions.double_dip
- Double Dip Solutions Ios https://apps.apple.com/sa/app/double-dip-solutions/id1578804344
- Ahil Nnu (Educational Game) https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=com.yoosin.ahilnnu
- Amawal Dictionnaire https://play.google.com/store/
 /apps/details?id=com.geekycorp.TifnaghDictionary
- Amawal Qamous (قاموس) https://play.google.com/store
 /apps/details?id=com.yoosin.TifnaghDictionaryArabic
- Loving Hands Hygiene Health & Wellness https://play.google.com/store /apps/details?id=apps.trichain.hairdresser